Guide to the Julian Sorell Huxley Papers, 1899-1980 MS 050
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Julian Sorell Huxley papers
1899-1980
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Huxley, Julian, 1887-1975
MS 050
91 Linear Feet (180 boxes)
Correspondence; diaries; mss. of writings; publications; materials on organizations including Unesco and Charles Darwin Foundation for the Galapagos Isles, conferences, including CCTA/IUCN Symposium on the Conservation of Nature and Natural Resources in Modern African States (Arusha, Tanzania, 1961), Darwin Centennial Celebration (University of Chicago, 1959), and Ciba Foundation Symposium on Man and His Future (London, England, 1963), travel, and his tenure as professor at Rice Institute; photos; memorabilia; and subject files, relating to Huxley's interests in biology (especially taxonomy, relative growth, evolutionary theory, genetics, and ethology), social evolution, eugenics, population control, cancer, conservation, and humanism; together with materials of his wife, Juliette Huxley. Correspondents include members of the Asquith, Darwin, and Huxley families and such scientists, artists, authors, and social figures as John Randal Baker, Sybille Bedford, Benjamin Britten, Jacob Bronowski, Paulo Carneiro, Kenneth Clark, Gavin De Beer, Theodosius Dobzhansky, Cyrus Eaton, T.S. Eliot, Richard Goldschmidt, Jane Goodall, Ernst Haeckel, J.B.S. Haldane, Alister Hardy, Jacquetta Hawkes, L.S.B. Leakey, Claude Levi-Strauss, Jacques Loeb, Konrad Lorenz, Rene Maheu, Ernst Mayr, P.B. Medawar, Henry Moore, Thomas Hunt Morgan, Herman J. Muller, Joseph Needham, Jean Piaget, Herbert Read, Bertrand Russell, Margaret Sanger, George Gaylord Simpson, Charles Singer, Stephen Spender, Pierre Teilhard de Chardin, Niko Tinbergen, Otto Warburg, H.G. Wells, Edmund B. Wilson, Leonard Woolf, and Solly Zuckerman.
(180 boxes)
Biographical Note
If I am to be remembered, I hope it will not be primarily for my specialized scientific work, but as a generalist; one to whom, enlarging Terence's words, nothing human and nothing in external nature was alien. Julian S. Huxley, Memories
Julian Sorell Huxley, the grandson of Thomas Henry Huxley and great-nephew of Matthew Arnold, was born June 22, 1887. The union of the Huxley and Arnold families brought about a happy combination of what Julian's younger brother Aldous would call blue genes, but the combined family traditions also imposed an obligation of intellectual excellence and social responsibility. This obligation was keenly felt by Julian Huxley from an early age. It was enhanced by his affinity for the interests which had earned his grandfather his place in the history of science, and thus, it soon became apparent that young Julian would be Thomas Huxley's intellectual heir as well as his grandson. This inheritance would prove both a joy and a burden, for while Julian Huxley achieved great renown as a scientist and popularizer of science, he was plagued, like his grandfather, by serious and debilitating attacks of depression. In spite of this he was able, throughout a long career, to contribute significantly to the fields of ethology, ecology and cancer research, and to act effectively as a powerful proponent of neo-Darwinism.
He was educated at Eton and Oxford, where he followed his own inclinations and his grandfather's example by studying Natural Science. His scientific interests were combined with literary talents which were officially recognized in 1908, when he was awarded the Newdigate Prize for English Verse at Oxford, an honor which he remembered with pride even after a lifetime of honors and accomplishments. (It is note-worthy and characteristic that he spent his prize money on a microscope.)
After completing his schooling, he began his career at the institution which had taught him: in 1910, he became a lecturer in Zoology at Oxford. Two years later, however, he departed from the course traditional to a young man of his academic interests and social background. He left England and Oxford to accept a position as Research Associate at the newly established Rice Institute in Houston, Texas, and by 1913 he had become Assistant Professor of Biology there. He remained in Houston until 1916 when he returned to Europe to take part in World War I.
After serving as an army intelligence officer in Italy, he came home to marry and to take up a position as Senior Demonstrator in Zoology at Oxford. From 1919 to 1925 he remained at Oxford, carrying out his famous axolotl experiments and participating in the university's expedition to Spitsbergen. In 1925 he became Professor of Zoology at King's College, University of London. But he did not remain long in that position. The following year he made a decision which, like his decision to teach at the Rice Institute, would move him away from the path followed by most of his fellow scientists. He accepted the invitation of H.G. Wells to collaborate on what would become The Science of Life, and in 1927 resigned his position at King's College. This meant a new direction for his career, for although he was Fullerian Professor of Physiology in the Royal Institution from 1927 to 1929, after that he held no academic position. For ten years he was a private person working to advance his ideas about the biological sciences not as a researcher nor as a teacher, but as a writer on scientific developments and their relationship to contemporary social issues.
In 1935 he accepted the position of Secretary of the Zoological Society of London. In this capacity he had the means to encourage solid research on animal behavior while introducing innovative methods for implementing his vision of the zoo as an educational institution. Unfortunately his leadership aroused the displeasure of some members of the Society, and in 1942 he resigned under pressure. He continued, however, his work as a writer and lecturer and was known throughout war-time Britain for his participation as a panel member of the BBC Brains Trust program.
The end of the war brought an opportunity for him to put many of his cherished ideals and projects into practice. True to family tradition, he had always viewed science, art and literature as part of a great whole. Thus when he became a member of the commission formed to plan what would become Unesco, he ensured that science would be an integral part of the educational and cultural institution. When in 1946 he became Unesco's first Director-General, he set out a program cosmopolitan in vision, one concerned with mankind in relationship with nature and with its past, one in which art and science were equally valued. He even went so far as to advocate his own solution to the troubling questions of modern society, his religion of scientific humanism, as an official basis for Unesco's philosophy. This he himself came later to find unwise. During his tenure as Director-General he also began to articulate fully the concerns which would occupy the later years of his life: the relation of overpopulation to poverty and ignorance, the necessity for the conservation of wilderness and wildlife, and the importance of the renunciation of parochial views on religion and politics. Finally, he came to stress even more strongly than before his optimistic belief that mankind can and should take control of its own environmental and biological destiny.
In 1948 his term of office with Unesco came to an end and Huxley was once again a private citizen. The remainder of his life was spent traveling, lecturing and writing in support of the causes to which he was devoted: evolutionary theory and its significance for potential human development, ecology and the preservation of wildlife and population control. He was honored often for his contributions to science and to society, receiving prizes and awards for his efforts in helping the general public to better understand contemporary scientific thought. In 1958 he received a knighthood. In 1965, in a culmination of work he began in his youth with his field studies of the behavior of the great crested grebe, he organized a Royal Society Symposium on the Ritualization of Behavior in Animals and Man, and in 1970 he received the International Union for the Conservation of Nature Gold Medal for outstanding contributions to scientific research related to conservation.
On February 14, 1975, at the age of 87, Sir Julian Huxley died. His life had been long, beginning in the Victorian era and ending in a world which his grandfather could scarcely have imagined. He served many of the causes with which the 20th century will no doubt become identified, and his influence on the development of contemporary biological science was considerable. Through his field studies of animal behavior and his synthetic approach to Darwinian evolutionary theory and Mendelian genetics, he helped determine the direction of modern biology. As an educator his influence was incalculable, for he taught not only such men as E.B. Ford and A.C. Hardy, but through his writings, perhaps millions of men and women as well. He was, moreover, known for his encouragement of aspiring scientists and scholars. In his catholic interests, in his belief in the interrelationship of science and arts, he extended his influence beyond the laboratory of the classroom and reached artists, writers, musicians, politicians and finally the general public. Such interests and such influence indicate that his desire to be known as one to whom nothing human and nothing in external nature was alien was fulfilled.
Scope and Contents
The collection documents Huxley's role as a synthesizer and educator who influenced thinking in many areas, including studies of taxonomy and relative growth, pioneering work in ethology, and important writing in the early twentiety-century synthesis of Mendelian genetics and Darwinian theory. His belief that evolution was not only biological but social and cultural as well led to interests in eugenics, population control, conservation and humanist movements. Linking scientists, science and other fields and science and the public, Huxley corresponded with such scientists, artists, writers and social figures as Kenneth Clark, J.B.S. Haldane, H.J. Muller, Bertrand Russell, Stephen Spender and H.G. Wells. Other materials found in the papers include original writings, publications of others, organizational, conference and travel materials, personal diaries, photographs and memorabilia.
Correspondence forms approximately one-third of the papers. It exemplifies the shape of the collection as a whole in that its volume increases steadily from the early years onward, peaking in the 1950s and 1960s and diminishing sharply during the times of Sir Julian's depressions. The most substantive part of the collection, the correspondence, not only includes letters from many twentieth-century intellectual, social and cultural leaders, but also provides the most information about Sir Julian and his myriad activities. Sir Julian's own writings -- published and unpublished - comprise another one-third of the collection.
Access Restrictions
This material is open for research.
Stored onsite at the Woodson Research Center.
Acquisition Information
In the spring of 1978, Juliette Huxley approached Rice University regarding the manuscript collection of her late husband, Julian Sorell Huxley. With work and support towards its acquisition by Mr. And Mrs. John F. Heard, Mr. And Mrs. C.M. Hudspeth, Mrs. Hardin Craig, Jr., Mr. And Mrs. Harris Masterson III, Professor Wilfred S. Dowden, the Friends of Fondren Library and British intermediary Anthony Rota of Bertram Rota, Ltd., the collection arrived at Rice in 1980, to be followed by Sir Julian's scientific library of approximately 1,200 books, pamphlets and journals. Separated from the main collection shortly before Sir Julian's death, a 1500-piece archive which Huxley called his box files was acquired from an American dealer as well. The collection was processed in 1983/1984 with the aid of a Higher Education Act Title II-C grant from the U.S. Department of Education. The manuscript processors were Sarah C. Bates and Mary G. Winkler; the assistant processor was Christina Riquelmy. Project director and assistant director were Nancy Boothe Parker and Lauren R. Brown.
General note
An index to this collection, which greatly facilitates access by correspondent name, is available online at: https://scholarship.rice.edu/handle/1911/27446
Other Finding Aids note
An index to this collection, which greatly facilitates access by correspondent name, is available online at http://scholarship.rice.edu/handle/1911/27446.
Index Terms
Subjects
Genetics; Mendel's law; Population policy; Science; Voyages and travels; Cancer; Eugenics; Conservation of natural resources; Birth control; Biology; Social evolution; Philosophy, Modern; Humanism; Evolution (Biology); Twentieth century
Places
Africa
Subjects (Persons)
Teilhard de Chardin, Pierre; Tinbergen, Niko, 1907-1988; Singer, Charles Joseph, 1876-1960; Spender, Stephen, 1909-1995; Wells, H. G. (Herbert George), 1866-1946; Wilson, Edmund B. (Edmund Beecher), 1856-1939; Warburg, Otto Heinrich, 1883-1970; Zuckerman, Solly Zuckerman, Baron, 1904-1993; Woolf, Leonard, 1880-1969; Lorenz, Konrad, 1903-1989; Loeb, Jacques, 1859-1924; Levi-Strauss, Claude; Leakey, L. S. B. (Louis Seymour Bazett), 1903-1972; Moore, Henry, 1898-1986; Medawar, P. B. (Peter Brian), 1915-1987; Mayr, Ernst, 1904-2005; Maheu, René; Piaget, Jean, 1896-1980; Needham, Joseph, 1900-1995; Muller, H. J. (Hermann Joseph), 1890-1967; Morgan, Thomas Hunt, 1866-1945; Simpson, George Gaylord, 1902-1984; Sanger, Margaret, 1879-1966; Russell, Bertrand, 1872-1970; Read, Herbert Edward, Sir, 1893-1968; Bronowski, Jacob, 1908-1974; Carneiro, Paulo E. de Berredo, 1901-; Clark, Kenneth, 1903-1983; De Beer, Gavin, Sir, 1899-1972; Dobzhansky, Theodosius, 1900-1975; Eaton, Cyrus Stephen, 1883-1979; Eliot, T. S. (Thomas Stearns), 1888-1965; Goldschmidt, Richard, 1878-1958; Goodall, Jane, 1934-; Haeckel, Ernst, 1834-1919; Haldane, J. B. S. (John Burdon Sanderson), 1892-1964; Hardy, Alister Clavering, Sir; Hawkes, Jacquetta, 1910-1996; Baker, John Randal, 1900-; Britten, Benjamin, 1913-1976; Bedford, Sybille, 1911-2006; Darwin family; Asquith family
Subjects (Corporations)
Unesco.; Zoological Society of London.; Charles Darwin Foundation for the Galapagos Isles.
- Series I: Early Materials, 1891-1909, 257634
  Scope and Contents note
  This series includes documents which predate 1909, the year of Huxley's graduation from Oxford. Here are some of the most personal glimpses of Huxley, in journals, drawings, schoolwork, poems and other writings. While the series contains a typescript of a poem by Enid Bagnold, dated 1908, most pre-1909 works by others have been separated to Series X: Manuscripts, Publications, and Addresses by Others, because there is evidence that Huxley did not receive them until after 1909. For other early materials, see Series XIV: Box Files, especially the file entitled "Birds and Bird-Watching". The series does not include visual materials and correspondence.
  - 1891-1899, 257645 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1899, 257644 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - [1900-1905], 257643 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 1900-1903, 257642 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 1904-1905, 257641 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 1906?-1909?, 257640 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - 1906?-1909?, 1906, 257639 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - 1907, 1908, 257638 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - 1907-1909, 257637 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - 1909, 257636 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - 1909, n.d. pre-1909?, 257635 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Series II: Family Correspondence, ca. 1900-1980, 257555
  This series consists of the lifetime correspondence with members of his large and talented family, except for some letters retained by the family. There are, for example, none from his grandfather Thomas Henry Huxley, and few from his brother Aldous. There are, however, letters from his brother Trevenen, his sister Margaret, his half-brothers David and Andrew and from his numerous Arnold, Arnold-Forster and Eckersley relatives. The family correspondence is filed in alphabetical order according to the name of the family member. A family tree appears in the index to this guide and a card file of family members is included in the first box in this series. Family correspondence is often addressed to both Sir Julian and his wife, or to Juliette individually. These letters are filed among those addressed to Huxley alone.
  Undated correspondence has been treated somewhat differently. In cases where the decade is known, the letters will be filed at the end of that decade. Letters without any date are filed together in alphabetical order by name of the correspondent at the end of the correspondence series. Note: Some correspondence can also be found in Series XIV: Box Files.
  - Arnold, Edward Augustus, 257633 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Arnold, Francis, 257632 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Arnold, Thomas, 257631 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Arnold-Forster, Christopher?, Anne, 257630 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Arnold-Forster, Katherine Cox, 257629 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Arnold-Forster, Mary Story-Maskelyne, 257628 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Arnold-Forster, Nigel, 257627 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Arnold-Forster, Val, 257626 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Arnold-Forster, William Edward, 257625 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Barkham, Selma Huxley, 257624 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Buzzard, Joan Collier, 257623 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Collier, Ethel Huxley, 257622 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Collier, Sir Laurence, 257621 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Cooke, Anne Huxley?, Geoffrey, 257620 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Crawshay-Williams, Rupert, 257619 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Darwin, Angela Huxley, 257618 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Darwin, George Pember, 257617 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Eckersley, Eva Pain, 257616 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Eckersley, Roger Huxley, 257615 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Eckersley, Thomas Lydwell, 257614 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Greenwood, Gillian Crawshay-Williams, 257613 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Harding, Marjorie Huxley, 257612 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Haynes, Oriana Waller, 257611 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Hovde, Ellen, 257610 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Hutton, Henrietta Cooke, 257609 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Huxley, Aldous Leonard, 257608 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Huxley, Anne Schenck, 257607 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Huxley, Sir Andrew Fielding, 257606 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Huxley, Anthony Julian, 257605 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Huxley, Christopher, 257604 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Huxley, David Bruce, 257603 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Huxley, Edmée Ritchie, 257602 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Huxley, Elspeth Josceline Grant, 257601 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Huxley, Francis John Heathorn, 257600 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Huxley, George Leonard, 257599 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Huxley, Gervas, 257598 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Huxley, Henrietta Heathorn, 257597 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Huxley, Henry (1865-1946), 257596 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Huxley, Henry (d.1968), 257595 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Huxley, Jocelyn Richenda Pease, 257594 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Huxley, Judith Wallet Bordage, 257593 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Huxley, Julia Arnold, 257592 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Huxley, Laura Archera, 257591 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Huxley, Leonard, 257590 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Huxley, Sir Leonard George Holden, 257589 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Huxley, Margaret, 257588 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Huxley, Marie Juliette Baillot, 257587 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Huxley, Matthew, 257586 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Huxley, Michael, 257585 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Huxley, Michael John Heathorn, 257584 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Huxley, Noel Trevenen, 257583 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Huxley, Ottilie de Lotbiniere Mills, 257582 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Huxley, Ouida Wagner, 257581 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Huxley, Rosalind Bruce, 257580 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Huxley, Sophy Wylde Stobart, 257579 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Huxley, Thomas, 257578 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Kilburn, Joyce Collier, 257577 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Moorman, Mary Trevelyn, 257576 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Neveux, Jeanne Nys, 257575 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Nicolas, Suzanne Nys, 257574 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Nys, Marguerite Baltus, 257573 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Roller, Henrietta (Nettie) Huxley, 257572 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Rothenstein, Diana (Sam) Arnold-Forster, 257571 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Scott, Thomas K., 257570 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Selwyn, Barbara, 257569 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Selwyn, Edward Gordon, 257568 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Selwyn, Lucy (Lulu), 257567 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Selwyn, Maud Stuart Dunn, 257566 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Sorell, Ernest, 257565 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Sorell, William Mervyn, 257564 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Tickell, Crispin, 257563 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Tickell, Renee Haynes, 257562 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Tickell, Thomas, 257561 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Trevelyan, Janet Ward, 257560 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Ward, Dorothy, 257559 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Ward, Mary August Arnold, 257558 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Whitridge, Arnold, 257557 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Whitridge, Lucy Arnold, 257556 (Box 4, Folder 33)
- Series III: General Correspondence, 1904-1980, 257238
  This correspondence includes the names of some of the most significant cultural, political and scientific figures of the 20th century. Moreover, the content is substantive, chronicling the immense variety of Huxley's interests and the influence which he exerted in the fields of science and culture, and includes letters to Huxley as well as drafts and carbon copies from him.
  This series contains not only "general" correspondence, but also a sampling of the variety of letters a prominent or controversial figure might expect to receive: petitions for aid, crank letters, even hate mail, as well as expressions of support and admiration. Of particular interest are the letters from the correspondents listed in the index at the back of this guide. This correspondence is filed chronologically with the other more general correspondence in order to present a more accurate picture of its context. No enclosures which are themselves correspondence are indexed. In cases where a letter has an attachment, both items are found filed under the date of the letter to which the attachment is affixed.
  Undated correspondence has been treated somewhat differently. In cases where the decade is known, the letters will be filed at the end of that decade. Letters without any date are filed together in alphabetical order by name of the correspondent at the end of the correspondence series.
  Various officers of organizations do not necessarily appear as individual correspondents in this index. Examples of such organizations include the United Nations, International Planned Parenthood Foundation, the Population Council, British Medical Association and others. Look for the organization name in the General Correspondence index.
  Note: Some correspondence in also to be found in Series XIV: Box Files.
  - 1904, 257554 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - 1905, 257553 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - 1906, 257552 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - 1907, 257551 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - 1908, 257550 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - 1909, 257549 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - 1910, 257548 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - 1911, 257547 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - 1912, 257546 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - 1913, 257545 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - 1914, 257544 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - 1904-1914?, 257543 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - 1915, 257542 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - 1916, 257541 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - 1917, 257540 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - 1918, 1914-1918?, 257539 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - 1919, 257538 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - January - June 1920, 257537 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - July - December 1920, 257536 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - 1920, n.d., 257535 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - January - June 1921, 257534 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - July - December 1921, 257533 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - 1921, n.d., 257532 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - January - June 1922, 257531 (Box 7, Folder 1)